<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life and death of Sir Matthew Hale, Knt. late Lord Chief Justice of England. Containing many pious and moral rules for humane conversation. : Also, many remarkable sayings and worthy actions of the said lord chief justice. : And many other things worth the readers perusal. / Written originally by Dr. Gilbert Burnet, now Bishop of Salisbury.</title>
            <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5829A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R175615</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504379</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504379</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171681</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77900)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171681)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2585:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life and death of Sir Matthew Hale, Knt. late Lord Chief Justice of England. Containing many pious and moral rules for humane conversation. : Also, many remarkable sayings and worthy actions of the said lord chief justice. : And many other things worth the readers perusal. / Written originally by Dr. Gilbert Burnet, now Bishop of Salisbury.</title>
                  <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by J. Bradford at the Bible in Fetter-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1700]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hale, Matthew, --  Sir, 1609-1676 --  Biography.</term>
               <term>Judges --  England --  Biography.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171681:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The LIFE and DEATH of Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Matthew Hale,</hi> Knt.</p>
            <p>Late Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Containing many Pious and Moral Rules for humane Converſation. Alſo, many Remarkable Sayings and Worthy Actions of the ſaid <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice.</hi> And many other Things worth the Readers peruſal.</p>
            <p>Written Originally by Dr. <hi>Gilbert Burnet,</hi> now Biſhop of
<hi>Salisbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>portrait of Matthew Hale</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>J. Bradford</hi> at the
<hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Fetter-Lane.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:171681:2"/>
            <head>The Life and Death of Sir <hi>Matthew Hale,</hi> Knight, late Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="body_of_text">
               <p>
                  <hi>MATTHEW HALE,</hi> was Born at <hi>Alderly</hi> in
<hi>Glouceſterſhire,</hi> the firſt of <hi>November,</hi> 1609. His Grandfather was <hi>Robert Hale,</hi> an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Clothier in
<hi>Wotton-under-edge,</hi> in that County, where he and his Anceſters had lived for many Deſcents; and they had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſeveral parcels of Land for the uſe of the Poor, which were enjoyed by them to this day. Thus he was deſcended rather from a good, than a Noble Family, and yet what was wanting in the inſignificant Titles of High Birth, and Noble Blood, was more than made up in the true worth of his Anceſtors. But he was ſoon deprived of the Happineſs of his Fathers Care and Inſtruction, for as he loſt his Mother before he was three years old, ſo his Father died be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was five; ſo early was he caſt on the Providence of God. But that unhappineſs was in a great meaſure made up to him: For after ſome oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition made by Mr.
<hi>Thomas Poyntz,</hi> his Uncle by his Mother, he was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the care of <hi>Anthony Kingſcot,</hi> of <hi>Kingſcot</hi> Eſquire, who was his next Kinſman, after his Uncles, by his Mother. Great care was taken of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, and his Guardian intended to breed him to be a Divine, and being inclined to the way of thoſe then called <hi>Puritans,</hi> put him to ſome Schools that were Taught by thoſe of that party, and in the 17th year of his Age, ſent him to <hi>Magdalen-Hall</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> where <hi>Obadiah Sedgwick</hi> was his Tutor. He was an extraordinary Proficient at School, and for ſome time at <hi>Oxford.</hi> But the Stage-Players coming thither, he was ſo much corrupted by ſeeing many Plays, that he almoſt wholly forſook his Studies. By this he not only loſt much time, but found that his Head came to be thereby filled with ſuch vain Images of things, that they were at beſt Improfitable, if not hurtful to him; and being afterwards ſenſible of the Miſchief of this, he reſolved upon his coming to
<hi>London,</hi> (where he knew the opportunities of ſuch Sights would be more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and Inviting) never to ſee a Play again, to which ho conſtantly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered. He was now ſo taken up with Martial matters, that inſtead of going on in his deſign of being a Scholar, or a Divine, he reſolved to be a Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier: and his Tutor <hi>Sedwick</hi> going into the
<hi>Low-Countries,</hi> Chaplain to the Renowned Lord <hi>Vere,</hi> and he reſolved to go along with him, and to trail a Pike in the Prince of
<hi>Orange</hi>'s Army; but a happy ſtop was put to this Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, which might have proved ſo fatal to himſelf, and have deprived the Age of the great Example he gave, and the uſeful Services he afterwards did his Country. He was engaged in a Suite of Law with Sir <hi>William Whitmore,</hi> who laid claim to ſome part of his Eſtate, and his Guardian being a Man of a retired temper, and not made for Buſineſs, he was forced to leave the Univerſity, after he had been three Years in it, and go to <hi>London</hi> to ſollicite his own Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs. Being recommended to Serjeant <hi>Glanvill</hi> for his Counſellor, and he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving in him a clear apprehenſion of things, and a ſolid Judgment, and a great fitneſs for the ſtudy of the Law, took pains upon him to perſwade him to forſake his thoughts of being a Soldier, and to apply himſelf to the ſtudy of the Law: and this had ſo good an effect on him, that on the 8th of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> 1629. when he was paſt the 20th Year of his Age, he was admitted into <hi>Lincolns-Inn:</hi> and being then deeply ſenſible how much time he had loſt, and that Idle and Vain things had over-run and almoſt corrupted his mind, he reſolved to Redeem the time he had loſt, and followed his Studies with a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence that could ſcarce be believed, if the ſignal effects of it did not gain it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171681:2"/>Credit. He ſtudied for many years at the rate of 16 Hours a day: he threw aſide all fine Clothes, and betook himſelf to a plain faſhion, which he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to uſe in many points to his dying day.</p>
               <p>Yet he did not at firſt break off from keeping too much Company with ſome vain People, till a ſad Accident drove him from it, for he with ſome other young Students, being invited to be merry out of Town, one of the Company called for ſo much Wine, that notwithſtanding all that Mr.
<hi>Hale</hi> could do to prevent it, he went on in his Exceſs till he fell down as dead be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, ſo that all that were preſent, were not a little affrighted at it, who did what they could to bring him to himſelf again: This did particularly affect Mr. <hi>Hale,</hi> who thereupon went into another Room, and ſhutting the Door, fell on his Knees, and prayed earneſtly to God, both for his Friend, that he might be reſtored to Life again; and that himſelf might be forgiven for giving ſuch Countenance to ſo much Exceſs; and he vowed to God, that he would never again keep Company in that manner, nor drink a Health while he lived: His Friend recovered, and he moſt Religiouſly obſerved his Vow, till his Dying day. And though he was afterwards preſt to drink Healths, particularly the Kings, which was ſet up by too many as a diſtinguiſhing mark of Loyalty, and drew many into great Exceſs after his <hi>Majeſties</hi> happy Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; but he would never diſpenſe with his Vow, though he was ſometimes roughly treated for this, which ſome hot and indiſcreet Men called Obſtinacy.</p>
               <p>This wrought an entire change on him: now he forſook all vain Company, and divided himſelf between the Duties of Religion, and the Studies of his Profeſſion; in the former he was ſo regular, that for 36 Years time, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver once failed going to Church on the Lord's day; this obſervation he made when an Ague firſt interrupted that conſtant Courſe, and he reflected on it, as an Acknowledgement of God's great Goodneſs to him, in ſo long a Continuance of his health. He took a ſtrict account of his time, of which the Reader will beſt judge, by the Scheme he drew for a Diary, which I ſhall inſert Copied from the Original, but I am not certain when he made it; it is ſet down in the ſame Simplicity in which he writ it for his own private uſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi rend="blackletterType">Morning.</hi> I. <hi>To lift up the heart to God in thankfulneſs for renewing my Life.</hi> II. <hi>To renew my Covenant with God in Chriſt.</hi> 1. <hi>By renewing Acts of Faith receiving Chriſt, and rejoyoing in the height of that Relation.</hi> 2.
<hi>Reſolution of being one of his People doing him Allegiance.</hi> III.
<hi>Adoration and Prayer.</hi> IV. <hi>Setting a Watch over my own Infirmities and Paſſions, over the Snares laid in our way.</hi> Perimus licitis.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi rend="blackletterType">Day Imployment.</hi> There muſt be an Imployment, two kinds. I. <hi>Our or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary calling, to ſerve God in it. It is a Service to Chriſt though never ſo mean.</hi> Col. 3. <hi>Here Faithfulneſs, Diligence, Chearfulneſs. Not to overlay my ſelf with more Buſineſs than I can bear.</hi> II. <hi>Our Spiritual Imployments: Mingle ſomewhat of God's Immediate Service in this day.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi rend="blackletterType">Retreſtments.</hi> I. <hi>Meat and Drink, Moderation ſeaſoned with ſomewhat of God.</hi> II.
<hi>Recreations.</hi> 1. <hi>Not our Buſineſs.</hi> 2. <hi>Sutable. No Games, if given to Covetouſneſs or Paſſion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi rend="blackletterType">If alone.</hi> I. <hi>Beware of wandring vain luſtful thoughts, fly from thy ſelf rather than entertain theſe.</hi> II. <hi>Let thy Solitary thoughts be profitable, view the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of thy Salvation, the ſtate of thy Soul, the Coming of Chriſt, thy own Mortality, it will make thee humble and Watchful.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi rend="blackletterType">Company. Do good to them. Uſe God's Name reverently. Beware of leaving an ill Impreſſion of ill Example. Receive good from them, if more knowing.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi rend="blackletterType">Evening. Caſt up the Accompts of the Day. If ought amiſs, Beg pardon. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſolution of more Vigilance. If well, Bleſs the Mercy and Grace of God that hath ſupported thee.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171681:3"/>Theſe Notes have an Imperfection in the Wording of them, which ſhews they were only intended for his Privacies. No wonder a Man who ſet ſuch Rul s to himſelf, became quickly very Eminent and remarkable. <hi>Noy</hi> the Attorney General, being then one of the greateſt Men of the Profeſſion, took early notice of him, and called often for him, and directed him in his Study, and grew to have ſuch Friendſhip for him, that he came to be called <hi>young Noy.</hi> He paſſing from the extream of Vanity in his Apparel, to that of neglecting himſelf too much, was once taken when there was a Preſs for the
<hi>King's</hi> Service, as a fit Perſon for it; for he was a ſtrong and well built Man: But ſome that knew him coming by, and giving notice who he was, the Preſs-Men let him go. This made him return to more decency in his Clothes, but never to any Superflulty or Vanity in them. Once as he was Buying ſome Cloath for a new Suit, the Draper with whom he differed about the Price, told him he ſhould have it for nothing, if he would promiſe him a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pound when he came to be Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England;</hi> to which he anſwered, That he could not with a good Conſcience wear any Man's Cloath, unleſs he payed for it; ſo he ſatisfied the Draper, and carried away the Cloath. Yet that ſame Draper lived to ſee him advanced to that ſame dignity.</p>
               <p>While he was thus improving himſelf in the Study of the Law, he not only kept the Hours of the <hi>Hall</hi> conſtantly in
<hi>Term-time,</hi> and continued then to follow his Studies with an unwearied diligence; and not being ſatisfied with the Books writ about it, or to take things upon truſt, was very diligent in ſearching all Records: Then did he make divers Collections out of the Books he had Read, and mixing them with his own Obſervations, digected them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Common-place Book; which he did with ſo much Induſtry and Judgment, that an Eminent <hi>Judge</hi> of the
<hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> borrowed it of when he was Lord Chief <hi>Baron:</hi> He unwillingly lent it, becauſe it had been Writ by him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was called to the <hi>Bar,</hi> and had never been throughly reviſed by him ſince that Time, only what Alterations had been made in the Law by ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Statutes, and Judgments, were added by him as they happened: but the
<hi>Judge</hi> having peruſed it, ſaid, That though it was Compoſed by him ſo early, he did not think any Lawyer in <hi>England</hi> could do it better, except he himſelf would again ſet about it. He ſet himſelf much to the Study of the <hi>Roman</hi> Law, and though he liked the way of Judicature in <hi>England</hi> by Juries, much better than that of the
<hi>Civil</hi> Law, where ſo much was truſted to the <hi>Judge;</hi> yet he often ſaid, that the true Grounds and Reaſons of Law were ſo well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in the <hi>Digeſts,</hi> that a man could never underſtand Law as a Science ſo well as by ſeeking it there, and therefore lamented much that it was ſo little Studied in <hi>England.</hi> When he was called to the
<hi>Barr,</hi> and began to make a Figure in the World, the late unhappy Wars broke out, in which it was no eaſie thing, for a Man to preſerve his Integrity, and to live Securely, free from great danger and trouble. He had read the Life of <hi>Pompenious Atticus,</hi> writ by <hi>Nepos,</hi> and having obſerved, that he had paſſed through a time of much Diſtraction, as ever was in any Age or State, from the Wars of <hi>Marius</hi> and
<hi>Scilla,</hi> to the beginnings of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his Reign, without the leaſt blemiſh on his Reputation, and free from any Conſiderable Danger, being held in great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem by all Parties, and courted and favoured by them: He ſet him as a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern to himſelf, and obſerving that beſides thoſe Virtues which are neceſſary to all Men, and at all times, there were two things that chiefly preſeroed <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus,</hi> the one was his <hi>engaging in no Faction,</hi> and <hi>medling in no publick Buſineſs,</hi> the other was his <hi>conſtant favouring and relieving thoſe that were loweſt,</hi> which was aſcribed by ſuch as prevailed to the Generoſity of his Temper, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured him much Kindneſs from thoſe on whom he had exerciſed his Bounty, when it came to their turn to Govern: He reſolved to guide himſelf by thoſe Rules as much as poſſible for him to do. He not only avoided all publick<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171681:3"/>Imployment, but the very talking of News, and was always both Favourable and Charitable to thoſe who were depreſt, and was ſure never to provoke any in particular, by cenſuring or reflecting on their Actions; for many that have Converſed much with him, have told me they never heard him ſpeak ill of any Perſon. He was imployed in his practice by all the <hi>King's</hi> party: He was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned Council to the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> and afterwards to the Bleſſed <hi>King</hi> himſelf, when brought to the infamous Pageantry of a Mock-Tryal, and offered to plead for him with all the Courage that ſo Glorious a Cauſe ought to have inſpired him with, but was not ſuffered to appear, becauſe the <hi>King</hi> refuſing, as he had good reaſon, to ſubmit to the Court, it was pretended none could be admitted to ſpeak for him. He was alſo Council for the Duke of
<hi>Hamilton,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Holland,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Capel:</hi> His Plea for the former of theſe I have publiſhed in the Memories of the
<hi>Duke's</hi> Life. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards alſo being Council to the <hi>Lord Craven,</hi> he pleaded with that force of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that the then Attorney-General, threatned him for appearing againſt the Government; to whom he anſwered, he was <hi>Pleading in defence of thoſe Laws, which they declared they would maintain and preſerve, and he was doing his duty to his Client, ſo that he was not to be daunted with Threatnings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſeeing him poſſeſt of ſo much Practice, and he being one of the Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenteſt Men of the Law, who was not at all affraid of doing his Duty in thoſe Critical Times, reſolved to take him off from it, and raiſe him to the <hi>Bench.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To theſe were added the Importunities of all his Friends, who thought that in time of ſo much Danger and Oppreſſion, it might be no ſmall Security to the Nation, to have a Man of his Integrity and Abilities on the <hi>Bench:</hi> and the Uſurpers themſelves held him in that Eſtimation, that they were glad to have him give a Countenance to their Courts, and by promoting one that was known to have different Principles from them; affected the Reputation of Honouring and truſting Men of Eminent Virtues, of what perſwaſion ſoever they might be, in relation to publick Matters. Not long after he was made a <hi>Judge,</hi> which was in the year
1653. when he went the Circuit, a Tryal was brought before him at
<hi>Lincoln,</hi> concerning the Murther of one of the Townſmen, who had been of the King's Party, and was killed by a Soldier of the Garriſon there. He was in the Fields with a Fowling-piece on his Shoulder, which the Soldier ſeeing, he came to him and ſaid, it was contrary to an Order which the Protector had made, <hi>That none who had been of the King's Party ſhall carry Arms;</hi> and ſo he would have forced it from him; But as the other did not regard the Order, ſo being ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than the Soldier, he threw him down, and having beat him, he left him: The Soldier went into the Town, and told one of his fellow Soldiers how he had been uſed, and got him to go with him, and lie in wait for the Man that he might be revenged on him. They both watched his coming to Town, and one of them went to demand his Gun, which he refuſing, the Soldier ſtruck at him, and as they were ſtrugling, the other came behind and ran his Sword into his Body, of which he preſently died. It was in the time of the Aſſizes, ſo they were both tryed: againſt the one there was no Evidence of forethought Felony, ſo he was only found guilty of Man-ſlaughter, and Burnt on the Hand; but the other was found guilty of Murther: And though Colonel <hi>Whaley</hi> that comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Garriſon, came into the Court and urged, That the Man was Killed only for diſobeying the Protector's Orders, and that the Soldier was but doing his Duty; yet the <hi>Judge</hi> regarded both his Reaſonings and Threatnings very little, and therefore he not only gave Sentence againſt him, but ordered the Execution to be ſo ſuddenly done, that it might not be poſſible to procure a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieve, which he believed would have been obtained, if there had been time enough granted for it. Another occaſion was given him of ſhewing both his Juſtice and Courage, when he was in another Circuit; he underſtood that the <hi>Protector</hi> had ordered a Jury to be returned for a Tryal, in which he was more<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171681:4"/>than ordinarily concerned: Upon this Information, he Examined the Sheriff about it, who knew nothing of it, for he ſaid he referred all ſuch things to the under-Sheriff, and having next asked the under-Sheriff concerning it, he found the Jury had been returned by order from <hi>Cromwell;</hi> upon which he ſhewed the State, that all Juries ought to be returned by the Sheriff or his lawful Officer; And this not being done according to Law, he diſmiſſed the Jury, and would not try the Cauſe: Upon which the <hi>Protector</hi> was highly diſpleaſed with him, and at his return from the Circuit, he told him in Anger <hi>he was not fit to be a Judge;</hi> to which all the Anſwer he made was, <hi>That it was very True.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another thing met him in the Circuit, upon which he reſolved to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded ſeverely: Some <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> had ruſhed into a Church, and had diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Congregation, while they received the Sacrament, not without ſome Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; At this he was highly offended, for he ſaid
<hi>it was intollerable for Men, who pretended ſo highly to Liberty of Conſcience, to go and diſturb others; eſpecially thoſe who had the Encouragement of the Law on their ſide:</hi> But theſe were ſo ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by ſome great Magiſtrates and Officers, that a ſtop was put to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; upon which he declared, he would <hi>meddle no more with the Tryals on the Crown-ſite.</hi> When <hi>Penruddocks</hi> Tryal was brought on, there was a ſpecial Meſſenger ſent to him requiring him to aſſiſt at it. It was in Vacation-time, and he was at his Country-Houſe at <hi>Alderly:</hi> he plainly refuſed to go, and ſaid, <hi>the four Terms and two Circuits were enough, and the little Interval that was between, was little enough for their private Affairs;</hi> and ſo he excuſed himſelf; he thought it was not neceſſary to ſpeak more clearly, but if he had been urged to it, he would not have been affraid of doing it. He was at that time choſen a Parliament-Man, (for there being then no Houſe of Lords, Judges might have been choſen to ſit in the Houſe of Commons) and he went to it, on deſign to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the Mad and Wicked Projects then on foot, by two parties, that had very different Principles and ends. Thus he continued adminiſtring Juſtice till the <hi>Protector</hi> dyed, but then he both refuſed the Mournings that were ſent to him and his Servants for the Funeral, and likewiſe to accept of the New Commiſſion that was offered him by <hi>Richard;</hi> and when the reſt of the Judges urged it upon him, and imployed others to preſs him to accept of it, he rejected all their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, and ſaid <hi>he could act no longer under ſuch Authority.</hi> He lived a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man till the Parliament met that called home the <hi>King,</hi> to which he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned Knight of the Shire from the County of <hi>Glouceſter.</hi> In that Parliament he bore his ſhare, in the happy period then put to the Confuſions that threatned the utter Ruin of the Nation. Soon after this, when the Courts in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> came to be ſettled, he was made Lord Chief Baron; and when the Earl of
<hi>Clarendon</hi> (then Lord Chancellor) delivered him his Commiſſion, in the Speech he made according to the Cuſtom on ſuch Occaſions, he expreſſed his Eſteem of him in a very ſingular manner, telling him among other things, <hi>That if the King could have found out an honeſter and fitter Man for that Imployment, he would not have advanced him to it;</hi> and
<hi>that he had therefore preferred him, becauſe he knew none that deſerved it ſo well.</hi> It is ordinary for Perſons ſo promoted to be Knighted, but he deſired to avoid having that Honour done him, and therefore for a conſiderable time declined all Opportunities of waiting on the <hi>King,</hi> which the <hi>Lord Chancellor</hi> obſerving, ſent for him upon Buſineſs one day, when the King was at his Houſe, and told his Majeſty there was his modeſt Chief Baron; upon which he was unexpectly Knighted. He continued eleven Years in that Place, managing the Court and all Procedings in it with ſingular Juſtice. It was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the whole Nation, how much he raiſed the Reputation and Practice of it: And thoſe who held Places and Offices in it, can all declare, not only the Impartiality of his Juſtice, for that is but a common Virtue, but his Generoſity, his vaſt Diligence, and his great Exactneſs in Tryals. This gave occaſion to the only Complaint that ever was made of him, <hi>That he did not diſpatch Matters
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171681:4"/>quick enough;</hi> but the great care he uſed to put Suits to an End, as it made him ſlower in deciding them; ſo it had this good Effect, that Cauſes tryed before him, were ſeldom if ever tryed again. Nor did his Adminiſtration of Juſtice lie only in that Court: He was one of the principal Judges that ſat in <hi>Cliffords-Inn,</hi> about ſettling the difference between Landlord and Tenant, after the Dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Fire of
<hi>London:</hi> He being the firſt that offered his Service to the City, for accommodating all the Differences that might have ariſen about the Rebuilding it, in which he behaved himſelf to the ſatisfaction of all Perſons concerned; ſo that the ſuddain and quiet Building ofthe City, which is juſtly to be Reckoned one of the Wonders of the Age, is in no ſmall meaſure due to the great Care which heand Sir <hi>Orlando Bridgeman</hi> (then Lord Chief Juſtice of the <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> afterwards Lord Keeper of the Great Seal of <hi>England</hi>) uſed, and to the Judgment they ſhewed in that Affair: ſince without the Rules then laid down, there might have otherwiſe followed ſuch an endleſs train of vexatious Suits, as might have been little leſs chargeable than the Fire it ſelf had been. But without detracting from the Labours of the other Judges, it muſt be acknowledged that he was the moſt Inſtrumental in that great Work; for he firſt by way of Scheme, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Rules upon which he and the reſt proceeded afterwards; in which his readineſs in <hi>Arithmetick</hi> and his skill in <hi>Architecture</hi> were of uſe to him.</p>
               <p>But it will not ſeem ſtrange that a Judge behaved himſelf as he did, who at the Entry into his Imployment, ſet ſuch excellent Rules to himſelf, which will appear in the following Paper Copied from the Original under his own Hand.</p>
               <q>
                  <list>
                     <head>
                        <hi rend="blackletterType">Things Neceſſary to be Continually had in Remembrance.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item>I. <hi>That in the Alminiſtration of Juſtice, I am intruſted for God, the King and Country; and therefore,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>That it be done,</hi> 1. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightly,</hi> 2.
<hi>Delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately,</hi> 3. <hi>Reſolutely.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. <hi>That I reſt not upon my own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding or Strength, but Implore and reſt upon the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Strength of God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>IV. <hi>That in the Execution of Juſtice, I carefully lay aſide my own Paſſions, and not give way to them, however provoked.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>V. <hi>That I be wholly intent upon the Buſineſs I am about, remitting all other Cares and Thoughts, as unſeaſonable and Interruptions.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>VI. <hi>That I ſuffer not myſelf to be prepoſſeſſed with any Judgment at all, till the whole Buſineſs and both Parties be beard.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>VII. <hi>That I never engage my ſelf in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of any Cauſe, but reſerve my ſelf unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced till the whole be heard.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>VIII. <hi>That in Buſineſs Capital, though my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture prompt me to Pity; yet to conſider, that there is alſo a Pity due to the Country.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>IX. <hi>That I be not too Riged in Matters purely Conſcientious, where all the barm is Diverſity of Judgment.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>X. <hi>That I be not byaſſed with Compaſſion to the Poor, or favour to the Rich, in point of Juſtice.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>XI. <hi>That Popular, or Court-Applauſe, or Diſtaſte, have no Influence into any thing I do in point of Diſtribution of Juſtice.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>XII. <hi>Not to be ſollicitous what Men will ſay or think, ſo long as I keep my ſelf exactly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rule of Juſtice.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>XIII. <hi>If in criminals it be a meaſuring caſt, to incline to Mercy and Acquittal.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>XIV. <hi>In Criminals that conſiſt merely in Words, when no more enſues, Moderation is no Injuſtice.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>XV. <hi>In Criminals of Blood, if the Fact be Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, Severity is Juſtice.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>XVI. <hi>To abhor all private Sollicitations, of what kind ſoever, and by whom ſoever, in matters Depending.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>XVII. <hi>To charge my Servants,</hi> 1. <hi>Not to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in any Buſineſs whatſoever,</hi> 2. <hi>Not to take more than their known F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es,</hi> 3.
<hi>Not to give any undue precedence to Cauſes,</hi> 4. <hi>Not to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend Council.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>XVIII. <hi>To be ſhort and ſparing at Meals, that I may be the fitter for Buſineſs.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </q>
               <p>He would neve receive private Addreſſes or Recommendations from the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Perſons in any matter, in which Juſtice was concerned. One of the firſt Peers of <hi>England</hi> went once to his Chamber and told him, <hi>That having a Suit in Law to be tryed before him, he was then to acquaint him with it, that he might the better underſtand it, when it ſhould come to be heard in Court.</hi> Upon which the Lord Chief Baron interrupted him, and ſaid, <hi>He did not deal fairly to come to his Chamber about ſuch Affairs, for he never received any Information of Cauſes but in open Court, where both Parties were to be heard alike;</hi> ſo he would not ſuffer him to go on: Whereupon his Grace (for he was a Duke) went away not a little diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and complained of it to the King, as a Rudeneſs that was not to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured.<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171681:5"/>But his Majeſty bid him
<hi>content himſelf that he was no worſe uſed;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>he verily believed he would have uſed himſelf no better, if he had gone to ſollicite him in any of his own Cauſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another paſſage fell out in one of his Circuits, which was ſomewhat cenſured as an affectation of an unreaſonable ſtrictneſs, but it flowed from his Exactneſs, to the Rules he had ſet himſelf: A Gentleman had ſent him a Buck for his Table, that had a Tryal at the Aſſizes; ſo when he heard his Name, he asked <hi>if he was not the ſame Perſon that ſent him Veniſon;</hi> and finding he was the ſame, he told him, <hi>He could not ſuffer the Tryal to go on, till he had paid him for his Buck;</hi> to which the Gentleman anſwered, <hi>That he never ſold his Veniſon, and that he had done nothing to him, which he did not do to every Judge that had gone that Circuit;</hi> which was confirmed by ſeveral Gentlemen then preſent: but all would not do, for the Lord Chief Baron had learned from <hi>Solomon,</hi> that <hi>A Gift perverteth the ways of Judgment,</hi> and therefore he would not ſuffer the Tryal to go on, till he had paid for the Preſent; upon which the Gentleman withdrew the Record; And at <hi>Salisbury</hi> the Dean and Chapter having according to Cuſtom, preſented him with ſix Sugar-Loaves in his Circuit, he made his Servants pay for the Sugar before he would try their Cauſe.</p>
               <p>He looked with great Sorrow on the Impiety and Atheiſm of the Age, and ſo ſet himſelf to oppoſe it, not only by the ſhining Example of his own Life, but by engaging in a Cauſe that indeed could hardly fall into better hands: And as he could not find a ſubject more worthy of himſelf, ſo there were few in the Age that underſtood it ſo well, and could manage it more skilfully. The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that firſt led him to Write about it was this. He was a ſtrict obſerver of the <hi>Lords-Day,</hi> in which, beſides his conſtancy in the publick Worſhip of God, he uſed to call all his Family together, and repeat to them the Heads of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, with ſome Additions of his own, which he fitted for their Capacities, and Circumſtances; and that being done, he had a Cuſtom of ſhutting himſelf up for two or three Hours, which he either ſpent in his ſecret Devotions, or on ſuch profitable Meditations as did then occur to his thoughts.</p>
               <p>While the Judge was thus imploying his time, the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Keyling</hi> dying, he was on the 18th of <hi>May,</hi> 1671. promoted to be Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England.</hi> He had made the Pleas of the Crown one of the Chief Studies, and by much ſearch, and long Obſervation, had compoſed that Great Work concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, formerly mentioned: He that holds the high Office of Juſticiary in that Court, being the Chief Truſtee, and Aſſertor of the Liberties of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; all People applauded this Choice, and thought their Liberties could not be better depoſited than in the hands of one, that as he underſtood them well, ſo he had all the Juſtice and Courage that ſo ſacred a Truſt required. One thing was much obſerved and commended in him, that when there was great Inequality in the Ability and Learning in the Councellors that were to Plead one againſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: He thought it became him, as the Judge, to ſupply that; ſo he would enforce what the weaker Council managed but indifferently, and not ſuffer the more Learned to carry the Buſineſs by the Advantage they had over the others in their quickneſs and skill in Law, and readineſs in Pleading, till all things were cleared in which the Merits and Strength of the ill defended Cauſe lay. He was not ſatisfied barely to give his Judgment in Cauſes, but did eſpecially in all Intricate ones, give ſuch an Account of the Reaſons that prevailed with him, that the Council did not only acquieſce in his Authority, but were ſo convinced by his Reaſons, that I have heard many profeſs that he brought them often to change their Opinions; ſo that his giving of judgment was really a learned Lecture upon that point of Law; and which was yet more, the Parties themſelves, though In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt does too commonly corrupt the Judgment, were generally ſatisfied with the Juſtice of his deciſions, even when they were made againſt them. His Impartial Juſtice, and great Diligence, drew the Chief Practice after him, into whatſoever<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171681:5"/>Court he came: Since, though the Courts of <hi>Common Pleas,</hi> the <hi>Exchequer</hi> and the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> are appointed for the Tryal of Cauſes of different Natures, yet it is eaſie to bring moſt Cauſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any of them, as the Council of Attornies pleaſe; ſo as he had drawn the Buſineſs much after him. both into the
<hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> and the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> it now followed him into the
<hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> and many Cauſes that were depending in the
<hi>Exchequer</hi> and not determined, were let fall there, and brought again before him in the Court to which he was now removed. And here did he ſpend the reſt of his publick Life and Imployment: But about four Years and a half after this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, he who had hitherto enjoyed a firm and vigorous Health, to which his great Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and the Equality of his Mind, did not a little conduce, was on a ſudden brought very low by on Inflamation in his Midriff, which in two days time broke the Conſtitution of his Health to ſuch a degree, that he never recovered it; He became ſo Aſthmatical, that with great difficulty he could fetch his Breath, that determined in a Dropſie, of which he afterwards Died. He under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>Phyſick</hi> ſo well, that conſidering his Age, he concluded his Diſtemper muſt carry him off in a little time; and therefore he reſolved to have ſome of the laſt Mouths of his Life reſerved to himſelf, that being freed of all Worldly Cares, he might be preparing for his Change: He was alſo much diſabled in his Body, that he could hardly, tho' ſupported by his Servants, walk through <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> or endure the Toil of Buſineſs; he had been a long time wearied with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions that his Imployment had brought on him, and his Profeſſion was become ungrateful to him; he loved to apply himſelf wholly to better Purpoſes, as will appear by a Paper that he writ on this ſubject, which I ſhall here Inſert.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt; If I conſider the Buſineſs of my Profeſſion, whether as an Advocate, or as a Judge, it is true I do acknowledge by the Inſtitution of Almighty God, and the Diſpenſation of his Providence, I am bound to Induſtry and Fidelity in it: And as it is an act of Obedience unto his Will, it carries with it ſome things of Religious Duty, and I may and do take Comfort in it, and expect a Reward of my Obedience to him, and the good that I do to Mankind therein, from the bounty, and beneficence, and providence of Almighty God; and it is true alſo that without ſuch Employments, civil Societies can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſupported, and great Good redounds to Mankind from them; and in theſe reſpects the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of my own Induſtry, Fidelity and Integrity in them, is a great Comfort and Satisfaction to me. But yet this I muſt ſay concerning theſe Employments, confidered ſimply in themſelves, that they are very full of Cares, Anxieties and Perturbations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly; That though they are beneficial to others, yet they are of the leaſt Benefit to him that is employed in them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly; That they do neceſſarily involve the party, whoſe Office it is, in great Dangers, Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and Calumnies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly; That they only ſerve for the Meridian of this Life, which is ſhort and uncertain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly; That though it be my Duty, faithfully to ſerve in them, while I am called to them, and till I am duly called from them, yet they are great Conſumers of that little Time we have here, which as it ſeems to me, might be better ſpent in a pious contemplative Life, and a due proviſion for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity: I do not know a better temporal Employment than
<hi>Martha</hi> had, in teſtifying her Love and Duty to our Saviour, by making proviſion for hm, yet our Lord tells her, That though ſhe was troubled about many things, there was only one thing neceſſary, and
<hi>Mary</hi> had choſen the better part.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>By this the Reader will ſee that he continued in his Station upon no other Conſideration, but that being ſet in it by the Providence of God, he judged he could not abandon that Poſt which was aſſigned him, without perferring his own private Inclination to the Choice <hi>God</hi> had made for him; but now that ſame Providence having by this great Diſtemper diſengaged him from the Obligation of holding a Place, which he was no longer able to diſcharge, he reſolved to reſign it.</p>
               <p>At laſt having wearied himſelf, and all his Friends, with his importunate Deſires, and growing ſenſibly weaker in Body, he did upon the 21ſt day of <hi>February,</hi> 28 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi>
167.56. go before a Maſter of the <hi>Chancery,</hi> with a little Parchment-Deed, drawn by Himſelf, and Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten all with his own Hand, and there ſealed and delivered it, and acknowledged it to be Enrolled, and afterwards he brought the Original Deed to the Lord Chancellor, and did formally ſurrender his Office. As ſoon as he was diſcharged from his great Place, he returned home with as much Chearfulneſs as his want of Health could admit of, being now eaſed of a Burthen he had been of late groaning under, and ſo made more capable of Enjoying that which he had much wiſhed for, according to his Elegant Tranſlation of, or rather Paraphraſe upon, thoſe excellent Lines in <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca's Thyeſtes. Act.</hi> 2.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Let him that will aſcend, the <hi>tottering Sect</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>courtly Grandeur,</hi> and become as great</l>
                  <l>As are his mounting Wiſhes: As for me,</l>
                  <l>Let ſweet <hi>repoſe</hi> and <hi>reſt</hi> my
<hi>Portion</hi> be;</l>
                  <l>Give me ſome <hi>mean obſcure Receſs,</hi> a Sphere</l>
                  <l>Out of the <hi>Road</hi> of <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> or the fear</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>falling lower;</hi> where I ſweetly may</l>
                  <l>My ſelf and dear retirement ſtill enjoy:</l>
                  <l>Let not my <hi>Life</hi> or <hi>Name</hi> be known unto</l>
                  <l>The Grandees of the Time, toſt too and fro</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Cenſures</hi> or <hi>Applauſe;</hi> but let my
<hi>Age</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Slide gently <hi>by,</hi> not <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>erthwart</hi> the Stage</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>publick Action,</hi> unheard, unſeen,</l>
                  <l>And unconcern'd, as if I near had been.</l>
                  <l>And thus, while I ſhall paſs my <hi>ſilent</hi> days</l>
                  <l>In <hi>ſhady privacy,</hi> free from the
<hi>Noiſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>buſtles</hi> of the mad World, than ſhall I</l>
                  <l>A good old <hi>Innocent Plebeian</hi> Dye.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Death</hi> is a mere <hi>Surpriſe,</hi> a very
<hi>Snare</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To him, that makes it his Life's <hi>greateſt Care</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To be a <hi>publick Pageant, known to all,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But <hi>unacquainted</hi> with himſelf, doth fall.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:171681:6"/>He could not lie down in Bed above a Year before his Death, by reaſon of the <hi>Aſthma,</hi> but ſat, rather than lay in it. He was attended on in his Sickneſs, by a Pious and Worthy Divine, Mr. <hi>Evan Griffith,</hi> Miniſter of the Pariſh; and it was obſerv'd, that in all the Extremities of his Pain, when ever he pray'd by him, he forbore all Complaints, or Groans, but with his Hands and Eyes lifted up, was fixed in his Devotions: Not long before his Death, the Miniſter told him, <hi>There was to be a Sacrament next</hi> Sunday <hi>at Church, but he believed he could not come and partake with the reſt; therefore he would give it to him in his own Houſe:</hi> But he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> No; <hi>his Heavenly Father had prepared a Feaſt for him, and he would go to his Father's Houſe to partake of it:</hi> So he made himſelf be carried thither in his Chair, where he received the Sacrament on his Knees, with great Devotion, which it may be ſuppoſed was the greater, becauſe he apprehended it was to be his Laſt, and ſo took it as his <hi>Viaticum</hi> and Proviſion for his Journey. He had ſome ſecret unaccountable Preſages of his Death; for he ſaid,
<hi>that if he did not die on ſuch a Day,</hi> (which fell to be the 25th of
<hi>November,</hi>) he believed he ſhould live a Month longer, and he died that very day Month. He continued to enjoy the free uſe of his Reaſon and Sence to the laſt Moment, which he had often and earneſtly prayed for during his Sickneſs: And when his Voice was ſo ſunk that he could not
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e heard, they perceived by the almoſt conſtant lifting up of his Eyes and Hands, that he was ſtill Aſpiring towards that Bleſſed State, of which he was now ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be poſſeſſed. He had for many Years a particular Devotion for
<hi>Chriſtmas-Day,</hi> and after he had received the Sacrament, and been in the performance of the publick Worſhip of that Day, he commonly wrote a Copy of Verſes on the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Saviour, as a fit Expreſſion of the Joy he felt in his Soul, at the return of that Glorious Anniverſary. There are 17 of thoſe Copies printed, which he writ on 17 ſeveral
<hi>Chriſtmas-Days,</hi> by which the World<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> has a Taſte of his Poetical Genius, in which, if he had thought it worth his time to have Excelled, he might have been Eminent as well as in other things; but he writ them rather to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain himſelf, than to merit the Lawrel. I ſhall here add one which has not been yet printed, and it is not unlikely it was the laſt he writ; it is a Paraphraſe on <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s</hi> Song; I take it from his blotted Copy not at all finiſhed, ſo the Reader is to make Allowance for any Imperfection he may find in it.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Bleſſed Creator, who before the Birth</l>
                  <l>Of Time, or e're the Pillars of the Earth</l>
                  <l>Were fix't or form'd, did'ſt lay that great Deſign</l>
                  <l>Of Man's Redemption, and did'ſt define</l>
                  <l>In thine Eternal Councels all the Scene</l>
                  <l>Of that ſtupendious Buſineſs, and when</l>
                  <l>It ſhould appear, and though the very Day</l>
                  <l>Of its Epiphany, concealed lay</l>
                  <l>Within thy Mind, yet thou wert pleas'd to ſhow</l>
                  <l>Some glimpſes of it, unto Men below,</l>
                  <l>In Viſions, Types, and Propheſies, as we</l>
                  <l>Things at a diſtance in Perſpective ſee:</l>
                  <l>But thou wert pleas'd to let thy Servant know,</l>
                  <l>That that bleſt Hour, that ſeem'd to move ſo ſlow</l>
                  <l>Through former Ages, ſhould at laſt attain</l>
                  <l>Its time, e're my few Sands, that yet remain</l>
                  <l>Are ſpent; and that theſe Aged Eyes</l>
                  <l>Should ſee the Day, when <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Star ſhould riſe.</l>
                  <l>And now thou haſt fulfill'd it, bleſſed Lord</l>
                  <l>Diſmiſs me now, according to thy Word;</l>
                  <l>And let my Aged Body now return</l>
                  <l>To Reſt, and Duſt, and drop into an Urn;</l>
                  <l>For I have liv'd enough, mine Eyes have ſeen</l>
                  <l>Thy much deſired Salvation, that hath been</l>
                  <l>So long, ſo dearly wiſh'd, the Joy; the Hope</l>
                  <l>Of all the Ancient Patriarchs, the Scope</l>
                  <l>Of all the Propheſies, and Myſteries,</l>
                  <l>Of all the Types unvail'd, the Hiſtories</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church unridl'd, and the bright</l>
                  <l>And Orient Sun ariſen to give Light</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the Joy of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Worlds Redeemer, bleſt <hi>Emanuel.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let this Sight cloſe mine Eyes, 'tis loſs to ſee,</l>
                  <l>After this Viſion, any Sight but Thee.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Thus he uſed to Sing on the former <hi>Chriſtmas-Days,</hi> but now he was to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to bear his part in the new Songs above; ſo that Day which he had ſpent in ſo much Spiritual Joy, proved to be indeed the Day of his Jubilee and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; for, between two and three in the Afternoon, he breathed out his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Pious Soul. His End was Peace, he had no Struglings, nor ſeem'd to be in any Pangs in his laſt Moments. He was Buried on the 4th of <hi>January,</hi> Mr. <hi>Griffith</hi> Preaching the Funeral Sermon, his Text was the 57th of <hi>Iſa.</hi> verſe 1. <hi>The
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171681:6"/>Righteous periſheth, and no Man layeth it to Heart; and Merciful Men are taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, none conſidering that the Right eous is taken away from the Evil to come.</hi> Which how fitly it was applicable upon this occaſion, all that conſider the courſe of his Life, will eaſily conclude.</p>
               <p>It has appeared in the Account of his various Learning, how great his Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were, and how much they were improved by conſtant Study: He roſe always early in the Morning, he loved to walk much abroad, not only for his Health, but he thought it opened his Mind, and enlarged his Thoughts to have the Creation of God before his Eyes. When he ſet himſelf to any Study, he uſed to caſt his Deſign in a Scheme, which he did with a great exactneſs of Method; he took no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on Truſt, but purſued his Enquiries as far as they could go; and as he was humble enough to confeſs his Ignorance, and ſubmit to Myſteries which he could not comprehend, ſo he was not eaſily impoſed on, by any ſhews of Reaſon, or the Bugbears of vulgar Opinions: He brought all his Knowledge as much to Scientifical Principles, as he poſſibly could, which made him neglect the Study of Tongues, for the bent of his Mind lay another way. Diſcourſing once of this to ſome, they ſaid, They looked on the Common Law, as a Study that could not be brought into a Scheme, nor formed into a Rational Science, by reaſon of the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtedneſs of it, and the Multipliciry of the Caſes in it, which rendred it very hard to be underſtood, or reduced into a Method;
<hi>But he ſaid,</hi> He was not of their Mind: and ſo quickly after, he drew with his own Hand, a Scheme of the whole Order, and Parts of it, in a large Sheet of Paper, to the great Satisfaction of thoſe to whom he ſent it. Upon this Hint, ſome preſſed him to Compile a Body of the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Law; It could hardly ever be done by a Man who knew it better, and would with more Judgment and Induſtry have put it into Method: But he ſaid, As it was a Great and Noble Deſign, which would be of vaſt Advantage to the Nation; ſo it was too much for a private Man to undertake: It was not to be Entred upon, but by the Command of a Prince, and with the Communicated En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of ſome of the moſt Eminent of the Profeſſion. He had great vivacity in his Fancy, as may appear by his Inclination to
<hi>Poetry,</hi> and the lively Illuſtrations, and many tender Strains in his Contemplations; but he look'd on Eloquence and Wit, as things to be uſed very chaſtly, in ſerious Matters, which ſhould come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſeverer Inquiry: Therefore he was both, when at the <hi>Bar,</hi> and on the
<hi>Bench,</hi> a great Enemy to all Eloquence or Rhetorick in Pleading: He ſaid, If the Judge or Jury had a right Underſtanding, it ſignified nothing, but a waſte of Time, and loſs of Words; and if they were weak, and eaſily wrought on, it was a more decent way of corrupting them, by bribing their Fancies, and biaſſing their Affections; and wondred much at that affectation of the <hi>French</hi> Lawyers, in imitating the <hi>Roman</hi> Orators in their Pleadings. For the Oratory of the <hi>Romans</hi> was occaſion'd by their popular Government, and the Factions of the City, ſo that thoſe who intended to excell in the Pleading of Cauſes, were trained up in the Schools of the <hi>Rhetors,</hi> till they became ready and expert in that luſcious way of Diſcourſe. It is true, the Compoſures of ſuch a Man as <hi>Tully</hi> was, who mixed an extraordinary Quickneſs, an exact Judgment, and a juſt Decorum with his skill in <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> do ſtill entertain the Readers of them with great Pleaſure: But at the ſame time, it muſt be acknowledged, that there is not that chaſtity of Style, that cloſeneſs of Reaſoning, nor that juſtneſs of Figures in his
<hi>Orations,</hi> that is in his other Writings; ſo that a great deal was ſaid by him, rather becauſe he knew it would be acceptable to hsi Auditors, than that it was approved of by himſelf; and all who read them, will acknowledge, they are better pleaſed with them, as <hi>Eſſays</hi> of
<hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Style,</hi> than as <hi>Pleadings,</hi> by which ſuch a
<hi>Judge</hi> as ours was, would not be much wrought on. And if there are ſuch Grounds to cenſure the performances of the greateſt Maſter in Eloquence, we may eaſily infer what nauſeous Diſcourſes the other Orators made, ſince in <hi>Oratory</hi> as well as in <hi>Poetry,</hi> none can do <hi>Indifferently.</hi> So our <hi>Judge</hi> wondred to find the
<hi>French,</hi> that<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171681:7"/>live under a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> ſo fond of imitating that which, was an ill Effect of the <hi>Popular Government</hi> of <hi>Rome:</hi> He therefore pleaded himſelf always in few Words, and home to the Point: And when he was a <hi>Judge,</hi> he held thoſe that Pleaded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, to be the main Hinge of the Buſineſs, and cut them ſhort when they made Excurſions about Circumſtances of no Moment, by which he ſaved much time, and made the chief Difficulties be well Stated and Cleared.</p>
               <p>He had a Soul enlarged and raiſed above that mean Appetite of loving <hi>Money,</hi> which is generally the <hi>Root of all Evil.</hi> He did not take the <hi>Profits</hi> that he might have had by his <hi>Practice;</hi> for in common Caſes, when thoſe who came to ask this Council gave him a Piece, he uſed to give back the half, and ſo made Ten Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings his Fee, in ordinary Matters that did not require much Time or Study: If he ſaw a Cauſe was Unjuſt, he for a great while would not meddle further in it, but to give his Advice that it was ſo: If the Parties after that, would go on, they were to ſeek another Councellor, for he would aſſiſt none in Acts of Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: If he found the Cauſe doubtful, or weak in point of Law, he always advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Clients to agree their Buſineſs: Yet afterwards he abated much of the Scrupuloſity he had about Cauſes that appeared at firſt view Injuſt, upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: There were two Cauſes brought to him, which by the ignorance of the Party or their Attorney, were ſo ill repreſented to him, that they ſeem'd to be very bad: but he enquiring more narrowly into them, found they were really very good and juſt; ſo after this he ſlackned much of his former Strictneſs, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to meddle in Cauſes upon the ill Circumſtances that appear'd in them at firſt. In his pleading he abhorred thoſe too common Faults of miſreciting Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, quoting Preſidents, or Books falſty, or aſſerting things Confidently; by which ignorant Juries, or weak Judges, are too often wrought on. He pleaded with the ſame Sincerity that he uſed in the other parts of his Life, and uſed to ſay, it was as great a Diſhonour as a Man was capable of, that for a little Money he was to be hired to ſav or do otherwiſe than as he thought: All this he aſcribed to the unmeaſurable Deſire of heaping up Wealth, which corrupted the Souls of ſome that ſeem'd to be otherwiſe born and made for great Things. When he was a Practitioner, Differences were often refer'd to him, which he ſetled, but would accept of no Reward for his Pains, tho' offer'd by both Parties together, after the Agreement was made; for he ſaid in thoſe Caſes he was made a Judge, and a Judge ought to take no Money. If they told him, he loſt much of his Time in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering their Buſineſs, and ſo ought to be acknowledged for it; his anſwer was (as one that heard it, told me) <hi>Can I ſpend my Time better, than to make People friends, muſt I have no time allowed me to do Good in.</hi> He laid aſide the Tenth Fenny of all he got for the Poor, and took great care to be well informed of proper Objects for his Charities: And after he was a Judge, many of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſites of his Place, as his Dividend of the Rule and Box-moneys, was ſent by him to the Jayls to diſcharge poor Priſoners, who never knew from whoſe hands their Relief came. It is alſo a Cuſtom for the Marſhal of the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> to preſent the Judges of that Court with a piece of Plate for a <hi>New-years-gift,</hi> that for the Chief Juſtice being larger than the reſt: This he intended to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, but the other Judges told him it belonged to his Office, and the refuſing it would be a prejudice to his Succeſſors; ſo he was perſwaded to take it, but he ſent word to the Marſhal, That inſtead of Plate, he would bring him the value of it in Money: And when he received it, he immediately ſent it to the Priſons, for the Relief and diſcharge of the Poor there. He uſually invited his poor Neighbours to Dine with him, and made them ſit at a Table with himſelf: And if any of them were Sick, ſo that they could not come, he would ſend Meat warm to them from his Table: And he did not only relieve the Poor in his own Pariſh, but ſent Supplies to the Neighbouring Pariſhes, as there was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for it: And he treated them all with the tenderneſs and familiarity that became one, who conſidered they were of the ſame Nature with himſelf, and<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171681:7"/>were reduced to no other Neceſſities but ſuch as he himſelf might be brought to: But for common Beggars, if any of theſe came to him, as he was in his Walks, when he lived in the Country, he would ask ſuch as were capable of Working, Why they went about ſo idly? If they anſwered, It was becauſe they could not find Work; he often ſent them to ſome Field, to gather all the Stones in it, and lay them on a Heap, and then would pay them liberally for their Pains: This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, he uſed to ſend his Carts, and cauſed them to be carried to ſuch places of the Highway as needed mending. But when he was in Town, he dealt his Charities very liberally, even among the Street-Beggars, and when ſome told him, That he thereby encouraged Idleneſs, and that moſt of theſe were notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cheats: He uſed to anſwer, That he believed moſt of them were ſuch, but among them there were ſome that were great Objects of Charity, and preſt with grievous Neceſſities; and that he had rather give his Alms to twenty who might be perhaps Rogues, than that one of the other ſort ſhould periſh for want of that ſmall Relief which he gave them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Judge</hi> was of a moſt tender and compaſſionate Nature; this did emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently appear in his Trying and giving Sentence upon Criminals, in which he was ſtrictly careful, that not a Circumſtance ſhould be neglected, which might any way clear the Fact: He behaved himſelf with that regard to the Priſoners, which became both the gravity of a Judge, and the pity that was due to Men, whoſe Lives lay at Stake, ſo that nothing of Jearing or unreaſonable Severity ever fell from him. He alſo examined the Witneſſes in the ſofteſt manner, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king care that they ſhould be put under no Confuſion, which might diſorder their Memory: and he Summed all the Evidence ſo equally when he charged the Jury, that the Criminals never complained of him. When it came to him to give Sentence, he did it with that Compoſedneſs and Decency, and his Speeches to the Priſoners, directing them to prepare for Death, were ſo Weighty, and ſo free of all Affectation, and ſo Serious and Devout, that many loved to go to the Tryals when he ſate Judge, to be edified by his Speches, and behaviour in them, and uſed to ſay, <hi>they heard very few ſuch Sermons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But though the pronouncing the Sentence of Death, was the piece of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, that went moſt againſt the Grain with him; yet in that, he could never be molified to any tenderneſs which hindred Juſtice. When he was preſſed to recommend ſome (whom he had Condemned) to his Majeſties Mercy and Pardon; he anſwered, <hi>He could not think they deſerved a Pardon, whom he himſelf had Adjudged to Dye.</hi> So that all he would do in that kind, was to give the King a true Account of the Circumſtances of the Fact, after which his Majeſty was to Conſider whether he would interpoſe his Mercy, or let Juſtice take place. His Mercifulneſs extended even to his Beaſts, for when the Horſes that he had kept long, grew Old, he would not ſuffer them to be Sold, or much Wrought, but ordered his Men to turn them looſe on his Grounds, and put them only to eaſie Work, ſuch as going to Market, and the like; he uſed old Dogs alſo with the ſame care: His Shepherd having one that was become blind with Age, he intended to have killed or loſt him, but the Judge coming to hear of it, made one of his Servants bring him home and fed him till he Dyed. And he was ſcarce ever ſeen more Angry than with one of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants for neglecting a Bird, that he kept, ſo that it Dyed for want of Food.</p>
               <p>He had a generous and noble <hi>Idea</hi> of GOD in his Mind, and this he found did above all other Conſiderations preſerve his quiet: And indeed that was ſo well Eſtaliſhed in him, that no Accidents, how ſudden ſoever, were obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to diſcompoſe him; of which an Eminent Man of that Profeſſion, gave me this inſtance: In the year 1666. an opinion did run through the Nation, <hi>That the End of the World would come that Year.</hi> This, whether ſet on by Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers, or advanced by thoſe who thought it might have ſome relation to the number of the Beaſt in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> or prompted by Men of ill Deſigns,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171681:8"/>to diſturb the publick Peace, had ſpread mightily among the People; and Judge <hi>Hale</hi> going that Year the
<hi>Weſtern</hi>-Circuit, it happened that as he was on the Bench at the Aſſizes, a moſt terrible Storm fell out unexpectedly, accompanied with ſuch flaſhes of Lightning, and claps of Thunder, that the like will hardly fall out in an Age; upon which a whiſper or a rumour run through the Crowd, That now was the World to end, and the Day of Judgment to begin; and at this there followed a general Conſternation in the whole Aſſembly, and all Men forgot the Buſineſs they were met about, and betook themſelves to their Prayers: This added to the horror raiſed by the Storm looked very diſmally; inſomuch that my Author, a Man of no ordinary Reſolution, and firmneſs of Mind, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, It made a great Impreſſion on himſelf. But he told me, That he did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Judge was not a whit affected, and was going on with the Buſineſs of the Court; From which he made this concluſion,
<hi>That his Thoughts were ſo well fixed, that he believed if the World had been really to end, it would have given him no conſiderable diſturbance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I ſhall now conclude all that I ſhall ſay concerning him, with what one of the greateſt Men of the Profeſſion of the Law, ſent me an abſtract of the Character he had made of him, upon long obſervation, and much converſe with him: It was ſent me, that from thence with other Materials, I might make ſuch a Repreſentation of him to the World, as he indeed deſerved, but I reſolved not to ſhred it out in parcels, but ſet it down entirely as it was ſent me, hoping that as the Reader will be much delighted with it, ſo the Noble Perſon that ſent it, will not be offended with me for keeping it entire, and ſetting it in the beſt light I could; It begins abruptly, being deſigned to ſupply the defects of others, from whom I had dealier and more copious Informations.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>He would never be brought to diſcourſe of publick Matters in private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, but in Queſtions of Law, when any young Lawyer put a Caſe to him he was very communicative, eſpecially while he was at the Bar: But when he came to the Bench, he grew more reſerv'd, and would never ſuffer his Opinion in any caſe to be known, till he was obliged to declare it Judically; And he concealed his Opinion in great Caſes ſo carefully, that the reſt of the Judges in the ſame Court could never perceive it: His reaſon was, <hi>becauſe every Judge ought to give Senten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e according to his own Perſwaſion and Conſcience, and not to be ſway'd by any reſpect or defence to another Mans Opinion:</hi> And by this means it hath happened ſome times, that when all the Barons of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer had delivered their Opinions, and agreed in their Reaſons and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments; yet he coming to ſpeak laſt, and differing in Judgment from them, hath expreſt himſelf with ſo much Weight and Solidity, that the Barons have immediately retracted their Votes and concurr'd with him. He hath ſat as a Judge in all the Courts of Law, and in two of them as Chief, but ſtill where ever he ſat, all Buſineſs of Conſequence followed him, and no Man was content to ſit down by the Judgment of any other Court, till the Caſe were brought before him, to ſee whether he were of the ſame mind: And his Opinion being once known, Men did readily acquieſce in it; and it was very rarely ſeen, that any Man attempted to bring it about again, and he that did ſo, did it upon great Diſadvantages, and was always lookt upon as a very contentious Perſon: So that what <hi>Cicero</hi> ſays of <hi>Brutus,</hi> did very often happen to him, <hi>Etiam quos contra Statuit Aequos placatoſque Dimiſit.</hi> Nor did Men reverence his Judgment and Opinion in Courts of Law only: But his Authority was as great in Courts of Equity, and the ſame reſpect and ſubmiſſion was paid to him there too: And this appeared not only in his own Court of Equity in the Exchequer Chamber, but in the Chancery too, for thither he was often called to adviſe and aſſiſt the Lord Chancellor, or Lord Keeper for the time being; and if the Cauſe were of difficult Examination, or intricated and entangled with variety of Settlements, no man ever ſhewed a more clear and diſcerning Judgment: If it were of<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171681:8"/>great Value, and great Perſons intereſted in it, no Man ever ſhew'd greater Courage and Integrity in laying aſide all reſpect of Perſons: When he came to deliver his Opinion, he always put his Diſcourſe into ſuch a Method, that one part of it gave light to the other, and where the proceedings of Chancery might prove Inconvenient to the Subject, he never ſpared to obſerve and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them: And from his Obſervations and Diſcourſes, the Chancery hath taken occaſion to Eſtabliſh many of theſe Rules by which it Governs it ſelf at this Day. He did look upon Equity as a part of the Common-Law, and one of the Grounds of it; and therefore as near as he could, he did always reduce it to certain Rules and Principles, that men might Study it as a Science, and not think the Adminiſtration of it had any thing Arbitrary in it. Thus eminent was this Man in every Station, and into what Court ſoever he was call'd, he quickly made it appear, that he deſerved the chief Seat there. As great a Lawyer as he was, he would never ſuffer the ſtrictneſs of Law to prevail againſt Conſcience, as great a Chancellor as he was, he would make uſe of all the Nicities and Subtilties in Law, when it tended to ſupport Right and Equity. But nothing was more Admirable in him, than his Patience: He did not affect the Reputation of Quickneſs and Diſpatch, by a haſty and Captious hearing of the Councel: He would bear with the meaneſt, and gave every man his ſull Scope, thinking it much better to looſe Time than Patience: In ſumming up of an Evidence to a Jury, he would always require the Bar to interrupt him if he did miſtake, and to put him in mind of it, if he did forget the leaſt Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance; ſome Judges have been diſturbed at this as a Rudeneſs, which he always looked upon as a Service and Reſpect due to him.</p>
                  <p>His whole Life was nothing elſe but a continual courſe of Labour and Induſtry, and when he could borrow any time from the Publick Service, it was wholly employed either in Philoſophical or Divine Meditations, and even that was a Publick Service too as it hath proved: For they have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned his Writing of ſuch Treatiſes, as are become the Choiceſt enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of wiſe and good Men, and the World hath reaſon to Wiſh that more of them were<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> printed: He that conſiders the active part of his Life, and with what unwearied Diligence and Application of Mind, he diſpatched all Mens Buſineſs which came under his Care, will wonder how he could find any time for Contemplation: He that conſiders again the various Studies he paſt through, and the many Collections and Obſervations he hath made, may as juſtly wonder how he could find any time for Action: But no man can wonder at the exemplary Piety and Innocence of ſuch a Life ſo ſpent as this was, wherein as he was careful to avoid every idle word, ſo 'tis manifeſt he never ſpent an idle day. They who come far ſhort of this Great Man, will be apt enough to think that this is a Panegyrick, which indeed is a Hiſtory, and but a little part of that Hiſtory which was with great Truth to be related of him: Men who deſpair of attaining ſuch perfection, are not willing to believe that any Man elſe did ever arrive at ſuch a height. He was the greateſt Lawyer of the Age, and might have had what Practicec he pleaſed, but though he did moſt Conſcientiouſly affect the labours of his Profeſſion, yet at the ſame time, he diſpiſed the Gain of it, and of thoſe profits which he would allow himſelf to receive, he always ſet apart a tenth Penny for the Poor, which he ever diſpenſed with that ſecrecy, that they who were relieved ſeldom or never knew their Banefactor: He took more pains to avoid the Honours and Preferments of the Gown, than others do to compaſs them. His Modeſty was beyond all Example, for where ſome Men who never attained to half his Knowledge, have been pufft up with a high conceit of themſelves, and have affected all occaſions of raiſing their own Eſteem by depreciating o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men: He on the contrary was the moſt obliging Man that ever Practiſed: If a young Gentleman happened to be retain'd to argue a point<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171681:9"/>in Law, where he was on the contrary ſide, he would very often mend the Objections when he came to repeat them, and always Commend the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man if there were room for it, and one good word of his was of more advantage to a young Man, than all the favour of the Court could be.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Having thus far purſued his Hiſtory and Character, in the publick and Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary parts of his Life, without interrupting the thread of the Relation, with what was private and Domeſtick, I ſhall conclude with a ſhort account of theſe.</p>
               <p>He was twice Married, his firſt Wife was <hi>Anne</hi> Daughter of Sir <hi>Henry Moore,</hi> of <hi>Faly</hi> in <hi>Berkſhire,</hi> Grandchild to Sir <hi>Francis Moore,</hi> Serjeant at Law; by her he had Ten Children, the four firſt Died young, the other ſix lived to be all Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried; And he out lived them oll, except his eldeſt Daughter, and his youngeſt Son, who are yet alive.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>THus lived and died Sir <hi>Matthew Hale,</hi> the
<hi>renounced</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England:</hi> He had one of the
<hi>bleſſings of Virtue</hi> in the higheſt meaſure of any of the Age, that does not always follow it, which was, that he was <hi>univerſally,</hi> much valued and admired by Men of all ſides and perſwaſions. For as none could hate him but for his Juſtice and Virtues, ſo the great eſtimation he was generally in, made, that few durſt undertake to defend ſo ingrateful a Paradox, as any thing ſaid to Leſſen him would have appeared to be. His Name is ſcarce ever mentioned ſince his Death, without particular accents of ſingular reſpect. His oppinion in points of Law generally paſſes as an uncontroulable authority, and is often pleaded in all the Courts of Juſtice: And all that knew him well, do ſtill ſpeak of him as one of the perfecteſt Patterns of Religion and Virtue they ever ſaw.</p>
               <p>The Commendations given him by all ſorts of People are ſuch, that I can hardly come under the Cenſures of this Age, for any thing I have ſaid concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him; yet if this Book lives to aftertimes, it will be looked on perhaps as a Picture, drawn more according to Fancy and Invention than after the Life; if it were not thoſe who knew him well, eſtabliſhing it Credits in the preſent Age, will make it paſs down to the next with a clearer Authority.</p>
               <p>As he was honoured while he lived, ſo he was much lamented when he died: And this will ſtill be acknowledged as as a juſt Inſcription of his Memory, tho' his Modeſty forbid any ſuch to be put on his Tombſtone.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>That he was one of the Greateſt Patterns this Age has Afforded, whether in his Private Deportment as a Chriſtian, or in his Publick Employments, either at the Bar or on the Bench.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="advert">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THe Beſt and moſt Experienced Remedy for <hi>Sore</hi> or
<hi>Weak Eyes,</hi> that ever yet was made known to the World, being of that wonderful Efficacy, that it infallibly diſpels any <hi>Humor</hi> or <hi>Salt Rheum</hi> diſtilling from the Head; and takes all Soreneſs, or Redneſs, or Swellings: It alſo ſtrengthens <hi>weak Eyes</hi> (ſometimes occaſioned by the <hi>Small-Pox</hi>) and will diſperſe any <hi>Film</hi> or <hi>Cataract</hi> grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the Eye, whereby the Sight oftentimes becomes dim: In a few times uſing this Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Remedy, to thoſe that will be perſwaded to uſe it often, it will preſerve the Sight to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible Age, and read the ſmalleſt of Prints. It being a Secret acquainted by a Gentleman in his long Study, whereby he has wrought wonderful
<hi>Cures</hi> among his Relations and Aquaintance; and now made Publick for the Benefit of all People that will make tryal of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For thoſe that are really <hi>Poor</hi> they ſhall have it for nothing; to Others for 6<hi>
                     <abbr>d.</abbr>
                  </hi> the Bottle. Only to he ſold at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Fetter-Lane,</hi> near
<hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171681:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
